<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tech on Allen&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://allenhsm.github.io/tags/tech/</link>
    <description>Recent content in tech on Allen&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This is a customized copyright.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 22:10:31 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://allenhsm.github.io/tags/tech/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Apache Kafka</title>
      <link>http://allenhsm.github.io/tech/cloud_infra_basics/apache_kafka/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 22:10:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://allenhsm.github.io/tech/cloud_infra_basics/apache_kafka/</guid>
      <description>Why Kafka? Problem of Request-Response Architecture: Kubernetes offers the ability to (de)scale your applications to respond to user requests in a meaningful amount of time. Process of request-response architecture: user sends a request to your application k8s master reroutes the request to an available pod, not enough pods HPA Still not enough VPA more requests Connection timeout Interruption If the number of user requests continue to increase beyond your K8s cluster resources, 1) your k8s master won&amp;rsquo;t have enough memory or processing power to reroute the incoming traffic, or 2) there are no available pods to process requests, and no more pods can be created.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deployment Orchestration</title>
      <link>http://allenhsm.github.io/tech/cloud_infra_basics/deployment_orchestration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 21:01:28 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://allenhsm.github.io/tech/cloud_infra_basics/deployment_orchestration/</guid>
      <description>Container Orchestration The automatic process of managing or scheduling the work of individual containers for applications based on microservices within multiple clusters. Orchestration tools: Kubernetes, Docker Swarm, Apache Mesos, CoreOS rkt
Kubernetes An open-source container management tool which automates container deployment, container (de)scaling, container load balancing Can group &amp;ldquo;n&amp;rdquo; number of containers into one logical unit called &amp;ldquo;POD&amp;rdquo;, easy to manage and deploy Features Automated bin packing: via packaging software and automatically placing it/containers based on their resource requirements and other constraints, while not sacrificing availability.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Containerization</title>
      <link>http://allenhsm.github.io/tech/cloud_infra_basics/containerization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 22:25:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://allenhsm.github.io/tech/cloud_infra_basics/containerization/</guid>
      <description>Virtual Machines to Containers VM is too heavy for a simple process as it boots a whole OS every time. Containers are isolated, but share OS, and where appropriate, also bins/libs. So SDE focuses more on app. Comparison:
Lightweight: Containerization avoids duplication of app Bins/libs, and only save the modifications did by different containers, without changing the original binaries. Security: VM is more secure because of full isolation while Container has only process level isolation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Virtualization</title>
      <link>http://allenhsm.github.io/tech/cloud_infra_basics/virtualization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 21:01:07 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://allenhsm.github.io/tech/cloud_infra_basics/virtualization/</guid>
      <description>Virtualization to create independent execution environment, leveraging the abstract form of the hardware capability.
More Defi of Virtualization abstracts the hardware of computing infrastructure into several different execution environments. Creates the illusion that each separate environment is running on its own private computing infrastructure. Makes servers, workstations, storage, network, and other systems independent of the physical hardware layer. It is the fundamental technology for cloud infrastructure. Virtual resources can be started and stooped easily and quickly on demand.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brief Intro to Cloud</title>
      <link>http://allenhsm.github.io/tech/cloud_infra_basics/intro_to_cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 03:10:21 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://allenhsm.github.io/tech/cloud_infra_basics/intro_to_cloud/</guid>
      <description>What is Cloud In simple words, Cloud = SCN (Lots of Storage + Computer C(omputation)ycles nearby + Network bandwidth)
In the industry, “Cloud” refers to large Internet services running on 10,000s of machines (Amazon, Google, Microsoft, etc.)
To be specific, Cloud is a model that offers following characteristics:
On-demand self-service: no human intervention needed to get resources Broad network access: access from anywhere Resource pooling: provider shares resources to serve multiple consumers Rapid elasticity Measured service Multi-tenancy Why Cloud Three main reasons:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cloud Infra Basics - 14848</title>
      <link>http://allenhsm.github.io/tech/cloud_infra_basics/cloud_infra_basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 02:03:20 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://allenhsm.github.io/tech/cloud_infra_basics/cloud_infra_basics/</guid>
      <description>Credit: This is a review and summary of the concepts and techniques I have learned so far in CMU course 14848. This course is designed and delivered by Professor Mohamed Farag, a helpful and passionate lecturer, a knowledgeable and chill guy. So most of the materials in this series of posts are from his lectures and slides.
Intro This course consists of two parts:
cloud infrastructure components coding in these components This series of posts will follow the same structure and review each specific topics separately.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
