<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>hadoop on Allen&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://allenhsm.github.io/tags/hadoop/</link>
    <description>Recent content in hadoop on Allen&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This is a customized copyright.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 04:56:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://allenhsm.github.io/tags/hadoop/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hadoop - YARN</title>
      <link>http://allenhsm.github.io/tech/cloud_infra_basics/hadoop_yarn/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 04:56:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://allenhsm.github.io/tech/cloud_infra_basics/hadoop_yarn/</guid>
      <description>Yarn Brief History Hadoop 1.x Core components: MapReduce and HDFS Structure: HDFS: NameNode + DataNodes MapReduce (MRv1): JobTracker + TaskTrackers JobTracker did everything: resource management, job scheduling, tracking tasks, failure handling Also a single point of failure and a scaling bottleneck MapReduce = computation engine + resource manager in one Only MapReduce jobs were supported Hadoop 2.x Now Hadoop has three logical layers: HDFS: storage layer NameNode + DataNodes YARN: resource management layer ResourceManager + NodeManagers + ApplicationMasters MapReduce (MRv2): computation layer Runs on top of YARN as one of many application frameworks Key improvements Separated resource management from computation MapReduce no longer monopolizes the cluster Allowed more engines: Spark, Tez, Flink, Storm, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hadoop - MapReduce</title>
      <link>http://allenhsm.github.io/tech/cloud_infra_basics/hadoop_mapreduce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 04:55:54 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://allenhsm.github.io/tech/cloud_infra_basics/hadoop_mapreduce/</guid>
      <description>Intro How traditional distributed system dealing with data: It is too complicated to build a distributed system from scratch Now MapReduce comes in and abbreviates this process by taking care of most parts, except for collecting results, and processing the data before handling failures. MapReduce Definition A programming model and an associated implementation for processing and generating large data sets with a parallel, distributed algorithm on a Hadoop cluster. It abstracts the problem from disk reads and writes, transforming it into a computation over sets for keys and values It works as a batch query processor that can run an ad hoc query against your whole data set and get result in a reasonable time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hadoop - HDFS</title>
      <link>http://allenhsm.github.io/tech/cloud_infra_basics/hadoop_hdfs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 01:27:18 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://allenhsm.github.io/tech/cloud_infra_basics/hadoop_hdfs/</guid>
      <description>Intro Motivation for Hadoop Handle big data! that exceeds single machine&amp;rsquo;s storage and computing capacity Storage and Analysis Storage capacity increases faster than then access speeds. Need parallel data access to get things done quickly 1 machine accessing 1000 GB is much slower than 100 machines, each is accessing 10 GB. Shared access for efficiency and scalability Challenges Analysis tasks need to combine data from multiple sources Need a paradigm that transparently splits and merges data Challenge of parallel data access to and from multiple disks Hardware failure Why Hadoop We need Open-source software framework for storing data and running applications on clusters of commodity hardware -&amp;gt; Hadoop is cheap to implement and expand Provides massive storage for any kind of data, enormous processing power and the ability to handle virtually limitless concurrent tasks or jobs -&amp;gt; Hadoop is scalable Hadoop Basics Component Architecture HDFS: Hadoop Distributed File System Designed to provide highly fault-tolerant and to be deployed on low-cost hardware MapReduce: A framework for processing data in batch - BSP (Bulk Synchronous Parallel) Enables distributed processing of large data sets across clusters of computers using simple programming models History HDFS Distributed File System A client/server-based application that allows clients to access and process data stored on the server as if they were on their own computer Client/Server arch: Clients request services and resources from a centralized server.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
